A Guide to the Betsy Brinson collection of AIDS epidemic exhibit materials, 1998, 2016-2017
Virginia Commonwealth University, James Branch Cabell Library
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library
Betsy Brinson collection of AIDS epidemic exhibit materials, 1998, 2016-2017
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
M 558
0.42 linear feet.
Brinson, Betsy
Content Description
The bulk of the collection consists of oral history interviews conducted by Betsy Brinson in 2016 and 2017 with people who volunteered and worked with affected communities in the Richmond area during the height of the AIDS epidemic in the 1980s and 1990s. There are seven different interviews on cassette, all about thirty to forty minutes long. Researchers will find content relating to major HIV/AIDS organizations in Richmond that served the community during the AIDS epidemic along with a detailed history of those organizations. These organizations include the Fan Free Clinic, Richmond AIDS Information Network, Central Virginia Aids Services and Education, along with others. Also found in the collection are interview notes, a booklet from Transformation Retreats, and a laminated newspaper clipping describing the exhibit.
The collection provides insight into how HIV/AIDS has and continues to affect the Central Virginia region, along with the many challenges and hardships that people affected by HIV experienced during the epidemic. A researcher doing research on non-profit organizations, specifically Richmond non-profits, will find this collection to be extremely useful.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Betsy Brinson in 2017.
Historical Information
The contents of this collection are associated with an exhibit presented at the Richmond Public Library in 2017 titled "The Modern Plague: Voices and Images of the Early AIDS Epidemic" by Betsy Brinson and Kathy Yost Benham which shared the stories of the communities and community allies who experienced the HIV/AIDS crisis in the 1980s and 1990s in central Virginia, particularly Richmond.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into two series: Series 1: Oral Histories, 2016-2017 and Series 2: Related materials, 1998, 2017
Gay activists -- Virginia -- Richmond.; Gay rights -- Religious aspects; Gay men -- Archives -- Virginia -- Richmond; Public health -- Virginia -- Richmond.; Brinson, Betsy
- Series 1: Oral Histories, 2016-2017
  - Jihad Abdulmumit oral history, 2017 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Length: 39:08
  - Chris Clarke oral history, 2016 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Length: 52:00
  - John Elliot oral history, 2016 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Length: 41:26
  - Ruth Fitzsimmons oral history, 2017 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Length: 56:32
  - Bill Harrison oral history, 2016 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Length: 48:24
  - Bob Higginson oral history, 2017 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Length: 50:33
  - Russell Webb oral history, 2017 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Length: 39:24
- Series 2: Related Materials, 1998, 2017
  - Exhibit newspaper clipping, 2017 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Transformation Retreats booklet, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 9)